<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Obedience active and passive due to the supream povver, by the word of God, reason, and the consent of divers moderne and orthodox divines; written not out of faction, but conscience, and with desire to informe the ignorant, and undeceive the seduced: by W.J. a welwiller to peace and truth.</title>
            <author>W. J., welwiller to peace and truth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J52</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E90_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860785</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E90[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Obedience active and passive due to the supream povver, by the word of God, reason, and the consent of divers moderne and orthodox divines; written not out of faction, but conscience, and with desire to informe the ignorant, and undeceive the seduced: by W.J. a welwiller to peace and truth.</title>
                  <author>W. J., welwiller to peace and truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Litchfeild, Printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A treatise printed in London with a counterfeit Oxford imprint" -- Madan.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The subjects duty to their lawfull king.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 24 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sovereignty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112910:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>OBEDIENCE</hi> ACTIVE and PASSIVE DUE TO THE SVPREAM POVVER, By the word of God, Reaſon, and the Conſent of divers moderne and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Divines; Written not out of <hi>Faction,</hi> but <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and with deſire to informe the Ignorant, and undeceive the Seduced:</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. J.</hi> a Welwiller to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>TIT. 3.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> Put them in mind, to bee ſubject to principalities and powers, and that they bee obedient, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 13.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> Let every Soule bee ſubject to the Higher powers.</p>
               <p>Principi, ſummum rerum judicium dii dederunt: Subditis obſequii Gloria relicta eſt, <bibl>
                     <hi>Tacitus lib. 6. Hiſtor.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Scutum potius quàm gladium, ſubditis in Tyrannose eſſe ſumendum, quos modeſtia &amp; patientia ſubditorum mitigat, contumacia verò exaſperat, <bibl>
                     <hi>Titus Livius, lib. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Leonard Litchfeild,</hi> Printer to the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, <hi>Anno</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112910:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112910:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a time, wherein many are become rather wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully then really ignorant, and more conceitedly then truly deſirous of Peace with Truth, to rectifie (if not ſatisfie) whom, this little treatiſe is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated unto publike view: wherein they ſhall find, (toward accompliſhing their deſire:) Truth from Heaven, tending toward peace on Earth; Truth being the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therof, Peace the end whereto it conduceth: And I ſuppoſed, there could bee no better meane, (under God) toward the compaſsing and procuring, that Peace, then by rightly informing each Subject of his duty, from the word of God, which is Truth: and therefore I dare bebold to ſay, that if the Truth herein ſincerely and cleerely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, be but lovingly embraced, and henceforth conſtantly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by us all; wee ſhall prove, both better ſervants to God our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and more loyall ſubjects to the King our Soveraigne: and ſo, not onely againe acquire, that great bleſsing of internall, externall, and eternall Peace to our ſelves, with confluence of all concommi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant felicity; but withall ſuddenly procure, from God and the King, that happy and all deſired <hi>Vnion,</hi> of his moſt ſacred Majeſty, with his Parliament, and People: whereby all our lawfull deſires may bee fully effected, which is the conſtant, fervent, and dayly prayer of the Authour.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112910:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112910:3"/>
            <head>The SVBIECTS duty to there lawfull <hi>KING.</hi> Conſiſting in ACTIVE and PASSIVE <hi>Obedience.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the King is the Head of the people; is evident by 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.17. where the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaith thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to King <hi>Saul</hi> from the Lord: <hi>When thou was little in thine owne ſight, waſt thou not made the Head of the Tribes of Iſrael? and the Lord annointed thee to be King over Iſrael?</hi> And by the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.7. where <hi>Ahijah</hi> the Prophet, bids King <hi>Jeroboams</hi> wife, <hi>Goe tell Ieroboam, Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael; I exalted thee from among the people, and made thee Prince over my people Iſrael.</hi> And 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.2. where <hi>Jehu</hi> the Prophet ſaith to King <hi>Baaſha</hi> from the Lord: <hi>I exalted thee from the duſt, and made thee Prince o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my people Iſrael:</hi> Which occaſioned <hi>Optatus</hi> to ſay, <hi>Super Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorem non eſt, niſi qui fecit Imperatorem;</hi> from which our Law too diſſents not; for in the yeare booke of 1. <hi>Henr.</hi> 7.10. and <hi>Finch fol.</hi> 81. it is ſaid, <hi>That the King is the head of the Common-wealth immediate under God;</hi> and therewith agreeth the more ancient Law, which tels us, <hi>Quod omnes ſub eo, ipſe autem ſub nullo, niſi tantum ſub Deo. Bracton. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. And therefore is it, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Exhorts all men to ſubmit themſelves unto the King, as to the Supreame:</hi> who is placed in that degree of eminency over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Not by himſelfe, (for Kings themſelves acknowledge in their ſtyles, that they are ſuch, <hi>Dei gratia,</hi> and therefore may not unfitly ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.3. <hi>He it is that made us and not wee our ſelves:</hi>) Neither by the people, (for the Iewes confeſſe, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.37. <hi>That Kings are ſet over them by God;</hi> and therefore, we often read in Scripture, That the King is called Gods <hi>Annoynted,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Annoynted,</hi> but never <hi>the peoples Annoynted.</hi>) And then, if neither by himſelfe, nor by the people, then ſurely by God alone; and truly God ſo aſſerteth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. They raigne not by themſelves, they raigne not by the people, But ſaith he, <hi>By mee Kings raigne,</hi> that is,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112910:4"/> by my ordination and appointment, being firſt ſetled, ſince upheld, and ſometimes miraculouſly preſerved in their raignes by mee, and by my will as the cauſe: For as the Prophets <hi>Ieremiah</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> tell us, <hi>The moſt high beareth rule over the Kingdomes of men, and giveth them to whomſoever hee will. Ier.</hi> 27.5.6. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.17. He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſole property of them; and therefore <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar. Dan.</hi> 2.37. ſaith, <hi>The God of Heaven hath given thee a Kingdome, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo <hi>Cyrus</hi> acknowledgeth <hi>Ezra.</hi> 1.2. ſaying, <hi>The Lord God of Heaven hath given mee all the Kingdomes of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee read <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14.15. That if the people would have a King, like other Nations, Then <hi>they ſhould in any wiſe ſet him King over them, whom the Lord their God ſhould chooſe.</hi> And 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.17. we read that God choſe <hi>Saul</hi> to raigne over his people; and 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.1. and 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.1. <hi>The Lord ſent Samuel to annoynt Saul to be King over his people Iſrael.</hi> And in the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.1. God ſaith to <hi>Samuel, I will ſend thee to Jeſſe the Bethleemite; for I have provided mee a King among his Sonnes,</hi> to wit, <hi>David,</hi> and at the 13. Verſe <hi>Samuel</hi> annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. And 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.7. God ſaith to <hi>David, I annoynted thee King over Iſrael.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> himſelfe after he was King, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.4. did acknowledge, that hee did not ſet up himſelfe to be King, neither was choſe by the people, but ſaith hee, <hi>The Lord choſe mee that I ſhould be King over Iſrael.</hi> And hereto agreeable, was the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of the Primitive Church, concerning Kings, (which had leaſt cauſe to favour them, in regard they were its perſecuters; and yet) <hi>Ireneus</hi> ſaith of them, <hi>Cujus juſſu naſcuntur homines, ejus juſſu conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuntur Principes:</hi> Thus wee ſee that Kings are provided for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and appointed by God; annoynted by his Prophets, and laſtly, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approved of by the people; and truly ſuch people as are his, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe will approve both his choyce and inſtitution, as wee read the Iewes did 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10 24. who when they ſaw <hi>Saul,</hi> whom God had appointed, choſe and annoynted for their King, they all ſhowted, and ſaid, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the inſtitution and office, ſo alſo the power of a King is derived from God; for as was before ſaid, by <hi>Daniel</hi> to <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar, Dan.</hi> 2.37. <hi>The God of Heaven hath given thee a Kingdome;</hi> ſo likewiſe doth hee adde thereto, <hi>power, ſtrength and glory,</hi> whereby it appeareth Kings have power from God, which our Saviour like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe acknowledgeth <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.11. where ſpeaking to <hi>Pilate,</hi> he ſaith,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112910:4"/> 
               <hi>Thou couldeſt have no power, except it were given thee from above;</hi> and therefore ſaith <hi>Tertullian, Inde illis poteſtas eſt, unde Spiritus,</hi> and that wee know is from God, not from the people: whereby it appeares, that what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. is very true, <hi>That there is no power but of God, and the powers that bee, are ordained of God.</hi> And therefore in that very place hee willeth and enjoyneth, <hi>That every Soule be ſubject to the higher powers.</hi> And writing unto <hi>Titus,</hi> hee willeth him, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. <hi>To put the people in mind, that they be ſubject to principalities and powers, and that they be obedient:</hi> in which places, by ſubjection, hee includes a neceſſity of not reſiſting: For ſuch who ſhall either diſ-reſpect the perſon, or diſobey the juſt power of the King, reſiſt the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and ſhall receive to themſelves condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as our Old, but damnation, as our New tranſlation renders, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew, in his booke <hi>de vita Moyſis,</hi> thus ſpeakes of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Kings; <hi>Regis officium eſt, jubere quae oportet fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri, &amp; votare à quibus abſtinere decet: caeterum, juſſio faciendorum &amp; interdictio ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendorum, propriè ad legem pertinet; atque ita conſequitur, quod Rex animata lex ſit, lex vero, ſit Rex juſtiſſimus.</hi> And our moſt gratious Soveraigne, not onely performes that good office, but withall admits of that rule, and for his peoples ſatisfaction, hath further proteſted before almighty God, not to governe them by any Arbitrary power of his owne, but to admit and propoſe the knowne lawes of this Realme, for his guide and the exact rule of his government: unto which I ſuppoſe every good Chriſtian will adhibite faith, and unto whom I hope, every loyall ſubject will yeild due obedience: and therefore how great a cauſe have wee to prayſe God, whoſe grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is pleaſed to ſet ſuch over us, as do ſet him in all their wayes before them? and how great cauſe have wee in all reſpects to honour him, who ruling us in goodneſſe, doth alſo rule himſelfe by good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Long may hee live among us; ever may he raigne by himſelfe, and royall poſterity over us, in glory and renoune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supreame, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.13. Not that Kings are ordained by men, or that men invented that government, (<hi>for the powers that bee are ordained of God, Rom.</hi> 13.1. and that Kings are is plainely manifeſted before, as alſo by 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. where God complaineth ſaying, <hi>It repenteth mee,</hi> (not that the people, but) <hi>that I have ſet up Saul to be King.</hi>) But,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112910:5"/> he cals Kingly Government an ordinance of man; (as <hi>Calvin, Beza, Marlorate, Aretius, Piſcator, Bucanus, Gerardus</hi> and <hi>Weemſe,</hi> have obſerved upon that text) becauſe the power, that is conferr'd by God upon men, is proper to men, exerciſed by men, and towards men; it is called an humane ordinance, <hi>ſubjective,</hi> becauſe men are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of it, and <hi>objective,</hi> becauſe it handles humane affaires; and laſtly, in reſpect of the end, being inſtituted for the good of man, and the conſervation of humane ſociety: So it appeareth by what hath beene ſaid, That Kings and Supreame Magiſtrates, are not politique inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of men, nor at firſt ordained by men, nor the power they are inveſted with, committed to them, from men, but from God: And therefore, let every ſoule bee ſubject to them; and as <hi>omnis anima,</hi> ſo <hi>ex omni animo,</hi> which ſhewes the manner; not with the body onely, but the mind alſo; not in ſhew alone, but indeed and in truth withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that to all juſt commands; yea, and to their unjuſt demands, if not contradictory to the will or word of God, by our Saviours exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27. who payed Tribute to the Polegatherers, for quietneſſe ſake, rather then offend or reſiſt, although nothing was due; but if their commands and demands bee contrary to Gods, then <hi>Deo potius, quàm hominibus,</hi> better obey God then man, by the example of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn, Acts</hi> 4.19. Yet ſo bee, they bee not diſſonant or diſcrepant from Gods, then Scripture wils us to yeild obedience thereto, not onely as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>for the Lords ſake,</hi> that ſo hee may bee honoured, who hath ordained Kings and powers, and would that we ſhould bee obedient to them; (as <hi>Aretius, Piſcator,</hi> and <hi>Lucas Oſiander,</hi> obſerve in their Comments upon that text:) but withall as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> enjoynes us, for <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake</hi> alſo. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. That ſo wee may retaine a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which wee muſt keepe <hi>voyd of offence,</hi> both towards <hi>God</hi> and towards <hi>Men. Acts</hi> 24.16. That it may witneſſe for us, that wee have not reſiſted Authority; for no man with a good conſcience, can reſiſt him, to whoſe power God hath made him ſubject; (as the ſame <hi>Piſcator</hi> and <hi>Oſiander,</hi> together with <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Bucanus</hi> have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon that text of Saint <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 3.5.) And therefore, becauſe wee muſt bee ſubject both for the <hi>Lords ſake,</hi> and for <hi>Conſcience ſake</hi> too, it will not bee amiſſe to conſider what a ſubjects duty to his Soveraigne is, and in what particulars it conſiſts.</p>
            <p>And firſt, wee muſt honour him; <hi>Give honour to whom honour is due,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>and honour the King</hi> ſaith Saint
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112910:5"/> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. and that muſt be by a reverend eſteeme of him, and an acknowledgement of him for our Superiour; by giving him due reſpect in our behaviour, and Titles of reverence in our words, as <hi>David,</hi> did to <hi>Saul.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.8. he ſtooped with his face toward the earth, and bowed himſelfe, and ſaid, <hi>My Lord the King,</hi> And as <hi>Arauna</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 24.20.21. and <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> 1 Kings 23.24 and <hi>Bathſheba</hi> to <hi>David</hi> at the 31. verſe of that Chapter, Who <hi>bowed her face to the earth, and did reverence to the King,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Let my Lord King David live for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, We muſt pray and give thanks to God for him: as S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>I exhort therefore that firſt of all, Prayers, Supplications and Thankeſgiving be made for all men, for Kings, &amp;c.</hi> and that as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> Pſal. 80.17. <hi>Let thy hand be upon the man of thy right hand; upon the ſonne of man, whom thou madeſt ſtrong for thy ſelfe;</hi> that is, O Lord, let thy hand of Providence, Power and Mercy be upon the man of thy right hand, and thine annoynted the King, ever redily and mightily to defend, preſerve and protect him; and upon him whom though thou reckoneſt among the Gods of the Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1 and 6. yet indeed, is but the ſon of man, whom thou haſt made ſtrong by Majeſtie and power, for thy ſelfe, to governe thy people as thy <hi>Vicegerant;</hi> or as our owne <hi>Liturgie</hi> teacheth us, That God would be pleaſed to be his defender and keeper and give him the victory over all his enemies, that God would ſo diſpoſe governe and rule the heart, of our Gracious King and Governour, that he might evermore have affiance in him, and in all his thoughts, words and works, ever ſeeke Gods honour and glory, and ſtudy, to preſerve the people committed to his charge, in wealth, peace and godlineſſe, and finally that after this life, he may attaine everlaſting joy and felicity.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We muſt feare him, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> wills us, Rom. 13.7. <hi>Give Feare to whom feare is due;</hi> and as <hi>Salomon</hi> Councells us. <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.21. ſaying, <hi>My Sonne, feare thou the Lord, and the King;</hi> and that with a feare of love, leaſt any hurt come to him; and a feare of awe, leaſt we offend and diſobey him. <hi>Salomon</hi> joynes them together, becauſe he that is a true ſervant of God, and feareth him, will be a true ſubject to the King and feare him alſo; For, it is but one and the ſame <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous feare,</hi> which firſt honoureth, God and then the King. And as <hi>Time Deum</hi> makes a good Chriſtian, ſo <hi>Time Regem,</hi> a good Subject; and the better Chriſtian, the better Subject. And to ſpeake Truth, it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112910:6"/> is God, that cauſeth this Feare in Subjects towards their King; for as S. <hi>Anſelme</hi> ſpeaketh very rightly, <hi>Nunquam poteſt fieri, niſi operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Dei, ut tot homines vni ſervirent, quem conſiderant vnius eſſe cum ipſis fragilitatis &amp; naturae: Sed quia Deus inſpirat Subditis timorem, &amp; obediendi voluntatem, contingit ita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, we muſt not murmur againſt him; For <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.8. and <hi>Num.</hi> 16.11. They that murmur againſt their Governours are ſaid to murmur againſt the Lord, becauſe they murmur againſt his ordinance and againſt his Miniſters; for <hi>they judge not for men but for the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. and <hi>Pro</hi> 8.15. <hi>by me Princes decree Iuſtice,</hi> ſaith God, and therefore what Chriſt ſaith in another caſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. may not unfitly be applied to them. <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me;</hi> for as the Apoſtles were the Meſſengers of Chriſt, ſo <hi>Kings are the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, We muſt not touch him with a virulent Tongue, like them in <hi>Ieremy,</hi> Ier. 18.18. who ſaid, <hi>Come let us ſmite him with the Tongue,</hi> that is, We muſt not ſpeake evill of him; no, though we receive wrong from him, by S. <hi>Paule's</hi> example <hi>Acts</hi> 23.5. towards <hi>Ananias;</hi> for ſo ſoone as he knew him to be the high Prieſt, he corrects himſelfe with a <hi>Scriptum eſt</hi> out of <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeake evill, of the Ruler of my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, We muſt not accuſe him: for <hi>where the word of a King is, there is power; and who may ſay to him, what doſt thou,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 8.4. and <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Iob, Is it fit to ſay to a King, Thou art wicked? Or to Princes, yee are ungodly?</hi> Iob. 34.18. And therefore we ſhould be ſo farre from judging amiſſe of his actions, That we ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excuſe what is done amiſſe by him, then accuſe him for it; and withall to ſuppoſe him ſo free in himſelfe, from doing any Act of Injuſtice, that we ſhould be ready to anſwer him, as did, both that wiſe woman of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 14 17 and alſo <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> 2 Sam. 19.27 <hi>My Lord the King is as an Angell of God, to diſcerne both good and bad, doe therefore, what is good in thine eyes.</hi> Wherefore though his actions may ſeem blame-worthy, yet we muſt not ſuppoſe them ſuch, and much leſſe accuſe him for them; and ſo <hi>Plantus,</hi> though an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could tell us, That <hi>Indigna, digna habenda ſunt, Rex quae facit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, We muſt not curſe him: for God hath prohibited it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not curſe the Ruler of my people,</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> gives us this leſſon by way of cauſion. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King, no, not in thy thought: for a bird of the ayre ſhall cary the voyce, and that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112910:6"/> which hath winges ſhall tell the matter;</hi> to teach us, That though Kinge and Governors have infirmities and vices, (which being men, they are equally ſubject too with others,) and ſo perchance may often do evill; yet we ought not to revile them, or curſe them therefore. Yea, though thou mayſt know the King to doe evill, and the land to ſuffer evill by his doing; yea, though thou mayſt know it by thine owne ſuffering of evil from him, yet, let not ſo much as thine hearts thought curſe him; as Doctor <hi>Iermyne</hi> in his Comments on that booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> hath obſerved upon that text, from S. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly, We muſt not touch him violently, nor lift up our hands againſt him. God hath inhibited it 1 <hi>Chro</hi> 16.22. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.15. Saying, <hi>Touch not mine annoynted,</hi> to wit, ſo as to doe him harme, or kill him; for as <hi>David</hi> ſaith to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. who can <hi>ſtretch forth his hands againſt the Lords annoynted, and be guiltleſſe?</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forbeare to deſtroy him. And we know how <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him, when as he onely did but cut off the skirt from King <hi>Sauls</hi> garment. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5. though he kild him not. For on whom Gods hand hath beene to annoynt them, he cannot endure any others hand ſhould be, to violate them: For there is ſuch neere alliance as it were, betweene God and them, Chriſt and them, and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> and them, as that they are not to be harmed the leaſt way, if either God, or Chriſt, or the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> can keepe us from it; For Kings participat with the name of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>I have ſaid yee are Gods:</hi> and with the name of Chriſt, for they are called <hi>Chriſti Domini, The Lords Annoynted,</hi> frequently in Scripture; and if they be annoynted, it is, with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> and power from above, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. as that learned and reverend Biſhop <hi>Andrewes</hi> in his Second Sermon of the conſpiracy of the <hi>Gowries.</hi> So in that they be annoynted with oyle, not tooke from the Marchants warehouſe, or the Apothecaryes ſhop, but from the Sanctuary; it ſhewes us, That <hi>Sacred</hi> is the office, whereunto they are deſigned; <hi>Sacred the power,</hi> wherwith they are endued; <hi>Sacred</hi> the perſons, wherto it is applied, &amp; therfore at no hand to be touched, either virulently with the Tongue, or violently with the hand.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, We ſhould not deſert him in his troubles and neceſſity, but adhere to him, and endure the extremity of Fortune with him: and even then anſwer him, as <hi>Davids</hi> Servants ſaid to him, when <hi>David</hi> was to flee with them from <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15 15. <hi>Behold thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are ready to doe, whatſoever my Lord the King ſhall appoint:</hi> and likewiſe with <hi>Ittai</hi> the <hi>Gittite</hi> to ſay and doe, as he did then to King
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112910:7"/> 
               <hi>David,</hi> at verſe the 21. <hi>As the Lord liveth, and as my Lord the King liveth, Surely in what place my Lord the King ſhall be, whether in life or death, even there alſo will thy Servant be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tenthly, In time of warre, if he goe forth to battaile, and there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelfe to danger, for the animation and incouragement of his Hoaſt, then, becauſe, <hi>he is worth ten thouſand of us,</hi> (as the people ſaid of King <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3. We muſt therefore be ſure that we be ready to reſcue him, and to venture our life for his deliverance, as wee read <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> one of <hi>Davids</hi> Generalls &amp; valiant men did, to ſuccour <hi>David</hi> from the hands of <hi>Iſbbi-benob the</hi> Philiſtim Gyant. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21 17. And then withall out of a feare of love, leſt he be againe endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; we ſhould with the Men of <hi>David</hi> (at the ſame verſe) ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Thou ſhalt goe no more out with us to battaile, that thou quench not the light of Iſrael;</hi> that is, leſt if thou periſh in the battaile, we looſe thee, who art not onely, the Ioy and the glory, but alſo the <hi>Light of Iſrael:</hi> where by the way, we may obſerve, the great eſtimation a people ſhould have of their King, <hi>viz.</hi> to eſteeme him as their <hi>Light;</hi> and withall, that when the <hi>Light of Iſrael is quenched,</hi> that is, when we looſe a good King, who is the <hi>Ioy</hi> and the <hi>Glory</hi> of his people, we are then rightly ſaid to be in darkeneſſe, and ſo expoſed to danger, as wanting a <hi>Light</hi> to guide us.</p>
            <p>Eleavently, We muſt not withhold his due from him: for our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our wills us <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21. to <hi>Give to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars:</hi> and S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.7. to <hi>render to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute</hi> &amp;c. Now becauſe Kings are the Miniſters of God for our good <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the good of Peace, Protection, Iuſtice, Religion &amp;c. at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending continually upon this very thing, therefore <hi>for this cauſe we pay tribute. Rom.</hi> 13.6. And truly in regard of their Care over us: we muſt not dare, but as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Reddere Caeſari quae ſua ſunt;</hi> That is, becauſe they keep our Tillage ſafe, they muſt have Tribute out of our Lands; and becauſe they keep the Sea ſafe, they muſt have <hi>vecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, Cuſtume, and Cenſum,</hi> Subſidy out of our goods: and therefore it is very remarkeable, That our Saviour never did any Miracle, about Honor or Money, except that one, which we read of <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.27. about giving Tribute to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> where, although nothing was due as may appeare by the two former verſes, yet ſaith Chriſt to <hi>Peter, Leſt we ſhould offend, goe thou to the Sea, and caſt an hooke and take up the fiſh that firſt commeth up: and when thou haſt opened his mouth, thou ſhalt find a peece of mony, that take, and give unto them for thee and me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112910:7"/>
            <p>Laſtly, We muſt be ſubject to them and obey them: for as <hi>Dion Caſſius</hi> hath well obſerved, <hi>Naturâ quipe id neceſſarium &amp; hominibus ſalutare, ut alij quidem imperent, alij vero pareant.</hi> And therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> wills <hi>Titus, Tit.</hi> 3.1. to put the people in minde, that <hi>they be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to principalities and powers, and that they be obedient.</hi> And againe, becauſe Chriſtians ſhould not ſuppoſe they were exempted from obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Heathen Governors, therfore the ſame Apoſtle, writing to the Roman Chriſtians, who though they lived under cruell <hi>Nero,</hi> that Perſecutor of the Church, and Infamy of his Age, and under his wicked ſubſtitutes, yet ſaith he, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers, and why?</hi> becauſe the powers that be, <hi>are ordained of God, and he that reſiſts the power, reſiſts the ordinance of God:</hi> and therefore be obedient.</p>
            <p>Now our ſubjection and obedience to the Kings and Governours who are ſet over us, and who are the Powers that are of God, is to permit their will to be done, <hi>aut a nobis, aut de nobis,</hi> that is, either of us, or on us; of us, when they command for Truth; on us, not by us, when they command againſt the Truth, to wit, Gods Truth &amp; Word; as we ſee by the axample of the Hebrew Midwives, whom the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> commanded, that when a Son was born to the Hebrew wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men they ſhould kill him. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.16. But <hi>the Midwives feared God, and did not as the King of Aegypt commanded them, but ſaved the men children alive.</hi> verſ. 17. for had they, they had beene guilty of murder, and therefore becauſe the Midwives feared God, <hi>He dealt well with them, and made them houſes.</hi> verſes 20.21. Alſo by the example of <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego. Dan.</hi> 3.18. Who would not <hi>worſhip the golden Jmage ſet up by Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> yet permitted his will to be done on them, by caſting them into the fiery furnace: verſes 20.21. and therefore God preſerved them, ſo that they had no harme, as we read in the ſame Chapter. And ſo <hi>Daniel,</hi> who though he was interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by King <hi>Darius, Dan.</hi> 6.9. Yet ceaſed not to pray unto God, <hi>three times a day.</hi> verſe 13. yet he permitted the Kings will to be done on him, (for he ſigned the decree) by caſting him <hi>into the Den of Lyons.</hi> verſe 16. So it appeareth, that we muſt be patients or Agents; Agents, when he is good and godly; patients, when he is tyranous and wicked; and then as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>It is thankworthy if a man for Conſcience towards God, endure griefe, ſuffering wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully:</hi> and unto a patient bearing of the Croſſe, we know we are called, for <hi>Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example,</hi> that we ſhould
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112910:8"/> 
               <hi>follow his ſteps,</hi> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> there tells us at verſe 21. Wherefore we muſt needs be obedient: becauſe <hi>all powers is of God;</hi> becauſe they bring with them the good of order; becauſe it is a ſinne to diſobey; becauſe judgement temporall and eternall, accompany the ſinne of Rebellion and diſobedience; becauſe governement is the meane of our weale; becauſe Kings are (as it were) hired by tribute, to ſerve their Servants, and take care for their ſubjects. Beſides, it is neceſſary that we ſhould obey, both <hi>ex neceſſitate finis &amp; pracepti;</hi> for hereby we ſhall doe that, which is acceptable to God, and profitable to our ſelves; acceptable to God, enjoyning obedience; profitable to our ſelves, as thereby enjoyning the good of government. <hi>That we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlynes &amp; honeſty,</hi> as S <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.2 (ſee Doctor <hi>Boys</hi> on the Epiſtle for the fourth Sunday after <hi>Epiphany.</hi>)</p>
            <p>And thus we ſee, That we are taught to obey Kings, by the Word, though they rule not alwayes by the Word: but what of that? As the neglect of their duty cannot excuſe the neglect of ours; ſo neither can the breach of their Oath, abſolve us before God, from our duties of Allegeance and Obedience to them, as <hi>Calvin, Aretius,</hi> and <hi>Marlorate,</hi> informe us. For we are bound to obey, as the perſon, ſo chiefly the power, becauſe it is of God.</p>
            <p>Nor muſt we only preforme this duty to good Kings and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith to ſervants, concerning their Maſters, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Be ſubject to your Maſters, with all feare, not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward:</hi> ſo may we lawfully ſay to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, concerning their Soveraignes, Be ye ſubject and obedient, not only to Good Kings, but alſo to the froward and wicked, as <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> aptly applying that text. So alſo devine <hi>Seneca,</hi> though an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, wills us, ſaying, <hi>Aequum atque Iniquum Regis Imperium feras:</hi> for we muſt conſider &amp; acknowledge with S. <hi>Chriſostom</hi> That, <hi>Reges quod ſunt, a Deo ſunt;</hi> and therefore, that every King, is either Gods golden Scepter, and ſo the Mirrour of his goodneſſe, when we enjoy peace and plenty and proſperity from God, under him, and by him; Or elſe he is Gods Iron Rod and Scourge, and ſo the Mirrour of his Iuſtice, as he ſaith of the Kings of <hi>Aſſiria. Eſay</hi> 10.5. by whom, God doth afflict and chaſtiſe his people, many times permitting him to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe taxes and hard lawes upon them, yea and ſometimes, the ſword it ſelfe too, when their ſins arive at that height, as to provoke Gods patience, and call for juſt and deſerved vengeance; For God ſends
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112910:8"/> wicked Princes, for the puniſhment of ſinners; ſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.23. When <hi>tho Tranſgreſſors are come to the full, a King of a fierce Countenance ſhall ſtand up:</hi> and he permits Hypocrites to raigne. <hi>Job</hi> 34.30. which both the vulgar, and <hi>Oſiander</hi> read, <hi>Qui fecit regnare hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam hominem, propter peccata populi.</hi> So that we ſee, if Kings be good, then as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>They are the Miniſters of God for our good:</hi> but if evill, we muſt with the Iewes. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.37. acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that they <hi>are ſet over us for our ſinnes,</hi> and yet both good and evill, by and from God.</p>
            <p>And truely, however ſome men dare adventure to call their lawfull, though evill Kings, Tyants, that ſo they might thereby ſhake of their due obedience to them, yet both Gods Word, and his owne peoples example, teach us otherwiſe. <hi>viz.</hi> to acknowledge, that even ſuch Kings, though Heathens, are <hi>his Annointed,</hi> as he ſaith of <hi>Cyrus, Eſay</hi> 45.1. (and ſo we read 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19 15. That <hi>the Lord ſent Elijah the Prophet to annoint Hazael to be King over Syria</hi>) Yea though wicked perſons, yet are his Servants, as he ſaith of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar. Ier.</hi> 25.9. and 27.6. and therefore to be obeyed; for ſaith God at the 8 verſe of that laſt Chapter. That, that <hi>Nation that will not put their necke under the yoke of (Nebuchadnezzar) the King of Babilon, I will puniſh ſaith the Lord, with the Sword, and with the Famine, and with the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> thereby teaching us, not to reſiſt or rebell againſt evill Kings, becauſe they are by him advanced to that Royall Majeſtie, and made his ſcourges, to puniſh us for our ſinnes. And as Gods word, ſo his owne peoples example, teacheth us obedience, to wicked Kings. For the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> while they were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> were (we know) aſwell the Subjects of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and yet notwithſtanding, the many cruelties and oppreſſions inflicted on them, by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who as we reade. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.14. <hi>made the Iſraelites lives bitter with hard bondage, in Mortar and in Bricke, and in all manner of ſervice in the field: all their ſervice, wherein they made them ſerve, was with rigour.</hi> Yet for all this, we doe not read, that ever they reſiſted or oppoſed him, but patiently endured thoſe afflictions, untill God ſaw their miſeries, and how they ſighed by reaſon of <hi>the bondage, and they cried, and their cry came up unto him. Ex</hi> 2.23. and 3.7. and then he ſent his Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> to deliver them, as we read. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.10. and who, when he was ſent, had not, (that we read of) any power committed to him, to incite the people to take up armes againſt <hi>Pharaoh</hi> their King, thereby to free themſelves
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112910:9"/> from their bondage; but was only to intreat <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to let them goe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.18. and to ſhew him Gods wonders, his plagues and judgements if ſo be he refuſed. And after, when as God was pleaſed, fully to avenge himſelfe, on <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for ſo oppreſſing his people; He choſe, rather miraculouſly to defeate and overthrow <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt in the Red-Sea, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.27.28. and ſo, wholly to deliver his people, both from their afflictions, and the hands of their enemies, Then he would permit them any liberty, to aſſume armes, whereby to avenge themſelves, for their injuries, on their lawfull, (though tyranous and cruell) King. And againe, we have their example, when they were lead Captives into <hi>Babylon, Nehem. cap.</hi> 9. Where after confeſſion, of Gods great goodneſſe and mercy towards them of old, and of their own wickedneſſe and the juſtneſſe of Gods puniſhment, ſpeaking of the Babiloniſh Kings to whom they were ſubjected, they likewiſe confeſſe and acknowledge, that they were ſet over them by God for their <hi>Sinnes; and that they had Dominion over their bodies,</hi> at verſe the 37. And therefore the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> chapter 29. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them from God (not to rebell, againſt thoſe Kings, to whom God rendered them ſubject, that ſo they might regaine their liberty, but) at the 7. verſe, <hi>to pray for the peace of Babylon to the Lord, for in the peace thereof, they ſhould have peace,</hi> and at the 10. verſe, to waite Gods leiſure for their deliverance, from that Captivily, and bondage, for ſaith he, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, After ſeventy yeares be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed at Babylon, I will viſit you, and performe my good words to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, in cauſing you to returne.</hi> And after, when God did full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his word to them, and delivered them, we know, that it was not, by ſtirring up their Spirits to Sedition, Reſiſtance, or Rebellion, but as <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe, hath recorded it, <hi>Ezra,</hi> 1.1.3. <hi>by ſtirring up the Spirit of King Cyrus, freely to diſmiſſe them and manumit them by his regall proclamacon;</hi> by both which examples, of the people of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Word of God, we are plainely taught <hi>Paſſive obedience,</hi> to the <hi>Supreame Power</hi> under afflictions, and to leave the redreſſe and revenge to God alone, to whom it properly appertaineth.</p>
            <p>And tauely, by the harmonious conſent, of many notorious and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved good Authors of the Proteſtant profeſſion of Religion, that I have conſulted, (to wit <hi>Calvin, Zanchy, Polanus, Piſcator, Martinius, Wollebius, Aretius, Bucer, Bullinger, Pomeranus, Marlorate, Buca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Szegedine, Wendelinus, Sharpius, Crotius, Alſtedius, Althuſius, Hugo Grotius,</hi> and the famous Authors of the <hi>Synopſis Purioris Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112910:9"/> viz. <hi>Polyander, Rivet, Wallens,</hi> and <hi>Thyſius,</hi> moſt of them, publicke profeſſors of Divinity; and our owne learned Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Boys,</hi> Maſter <hi>Perkins,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Downeham,</hi> all Orthodox men and good writers; beſides, <hi>Oſiander, Vogelius, Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tericus, Gerardus Brochmandus, Gravius, Caſmannus,</hi> and <hi>Schrode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, (Lutherans)</hi> and the two famous Frenchmen, <hi>(Peter Charon,</hi> and <hi>Peter de la Primanday,)</hi> who grounding their judgements upon Scripture, doe all conclude, That we ought to obey <hi>Princes,</hi> though wicked men, in all things, that contradict not the revealed will or Word of God: but if ſo be, they command things unlawfull and which are againſt that Rule of Gods will and Word, then as we muſt not obey them, by doing; ſo neither reſiſt them, by rebelling; but either, patiently ſuffer their wills to be done on us, though not by us; or otherwiſe, fly from them, as <hi>David</hi> did from <hi>Saul.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.12 18. and as our Saviour Chriſt did from <hi>Herod, Mat.</hi> 2.13. and as he adviſeth his Deſciples to doe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.23. <hi>When they perſecute you in one City, fly into another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we ſee, That though Kings be not godly, but wicked perſons, yet honour and obedience is to be done unto them, becauſe it is God that hath ſet them up over us, though in his <hi>wrath</hi> againſt us, as he ſaith, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.11. and therefore, though their ſinnes may make us diſaffect their perſons, yet muſt we yeeld obedience, to the power they are inveſted with, becauſe it is of God. For as the learned <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> well obſerves (<hi>li.</hi> 1. <hi>de jure belli &amp; paris, ca:</hi> 2. <hi>Set.</hi> 7.) <hi>Sicut olim, pia crant Sacrificia ſecundum legem, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ab impijs Sacerdotibus celebrata: Sic pia res eſt Imperium, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ab Impio teneatur.</hi> And ſo <hi>Althuſius</hi> from <hi>Aretius, vitia Perſonae, non tollunt Officium illius.</hi> For we ought not to obey a <hi>Superiour,</hi> becauſe he is worthy, and worthily commandeth, but becauſe he is a Superiour, ſaith <hi>Peter Charon. ca.</hi> 16. of his 3 booke of Wiſedome. Wherfore, Men cannot ſafely reſiſt that <hi>Authotity,</hi> nor deſpiſe that power of Kings, without they will, as acquire the name; ſo juſtly incurre the puniſhmen of Rebells: whom to oppoſe and reſiſt, as it is commendable, ſo, to ſubdue and deſtroy is warrantable by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for, <hi>Rebellion is as the ſinne of Witch-craft,</hi> as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaith to <hi>Saul,</hi> from God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. And <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a Witch to live,</hi> ſaith God him ſelfe. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22, 18.</p>
            <p>Now, the Scripture records, and ſhewes us, many Iudgements of, God upon <hi>Rebells, Revolters, Seditious</hi> and <hi>Traiterous</hi> perſons, and the fearefull ends they came to; That ſo we avoyding the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112910:10"/> ſinnes, might thereby alſo evade the puniſhment: for, what a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end is it, to have the Earth open her mouth, and ſwallow us up quicke, as it did <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram, Num.</hi> 16.32. and to be conſumed by fire from the Lord, as the Two hundred and fifty Princes of <hi>Jſrael</hi> were, at the 35. verſe of that Chapter; to hang by the haire of our head, betweene the Heaven and the Earth as unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of either, and whileſt yet alive, to have our heart opened, as <hi>Abſol m,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.9.14. to be ſlaine, and drawen and dragged from the place, as <hi>Ioab</hi> was, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.34. to be hanged, as <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Tereſh,</hi> the Chamberlaines of King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> were, <hi>Eſther.</hi> 2.23. to have ones head chopped off, as <hi>Sheba's</hi> was, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20 22. and both it and ones quarters hanged up, as <hi>Baanah's</hi> and <hi>Rechabs</hi> were, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 4.11. to have ones Lands, and Livelihood ſeiſed upon and given to ſtrangers, ones Iſſue miſerable for our ſakes, and to be <hi>Damnatae memoriae,</hi> both ones name and memory as a curſe to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as we read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.11.10.13. but were this all, (though this be much and fearefull too,) there might yet remaine ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; but that ſuch perſons might be wholly comfortleſſe, eternall puniſhments remaine, to be inflicted and ſucceed theſe temporall: ſo ſaith S. <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 13.2. <hi>They that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> And therefore that we may not come to ſuch untimely ends, we muſt be carefull to avoyd ſuch particulars, as making us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with the perſons, in the facts of Treaſon, Rebellion, and Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; may make us ſhare alſo, in the Act of puniſhment with them. Now Scripture ſhewes us many wayes, whereby a man may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with others, and ſo become guilty: as by being a Champion, or Leader for them; as <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>Adonijah</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1, 7. by being a Spokeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Orator for them, as <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> to his Crew, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.4. by blowing the Trumpet, that is animating them, and ſetting them on; as <hi>Sheba,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1. by giving them ſhrewd advice to manage their matters and affaires; as <hi>Achitophel</hi> to <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.21. By praying for their ſucceſſe: that was all <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt could do, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. by bruiting infamous Speeches, or libells of the King; as <hi>Shemei</hi> did, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 16.7. by harbouring or receiving them; as the City <hi>Abel</hi> did <hi>Sheba,</hi> and ſhould have beene ſacked for it, had not the wiſedome of the wiſe woman prevented it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.14.16. by furniſhing them with money, or ſupplies otherwiſe; as the men of <hi>Sichem,</hi> to <hi>Abimelech, Iudges.</hi> 9.4. by being (if not partie yet) privie to it, and not oppoſing, as <hi>David</hi> had beene to <hi>Sauls</hi> death,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112910:10"/> if he had not hindred <hi>Abiſhal,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. or by being, at the leaſt privie, and not diſcloſing it; which had beene <hi>Mordecai's,</hi> caſe, if he had concealed the Eunuches <hi>Treaſon, Eſther,</hi> 2.22. And laſtly, (which is as bad as any of the reſt,) by ſpeaking, or writing, in praiſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, either of the deed or the doers; which is their caſe, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.41. calling <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company, <hi>The people of the Lord;</hi> for ſure if the Conſenter be in, the Commender much more. And as Gods Law, ſo likewiſe the Statute and Common Law of this <hi>Realme,</hi> (mongſt many other) have declared one grand way, wherby a man may not only become actually guilty, but alſo partake with the guilty in the Act. And that is thus expreſt, by the Statute of 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. <hi>If a man doe leavy warre, againſt our Lord the King, in his Realme; or be adherent to the Kings Enemies in his Realme, giving to them ayd and comfort, in the Realme or elſewhere, and thereof be probably attainted, of open deed, by people of their condition, he is guilty of Treaſon.</hi> And our Bookes, expound this branch of that Statute thus, <hi>He doth leavye warre againſt the King, who doth encounter in fight, ſuch as be aſſiſting to the King, in his warres; And he is adherent and giveth comfort to the Kings Enemies, who, in open field, giveth battaile to the Kinge friends, for taking the Kings part.</hi> So <hi>Poulton de pace Regis &amp; Regni. Tit. Treaſons.</hi> 4. <hi>Daltons Iuſtice of peace, fo.</hi> 224. and the yeere booke of, 45. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.25. and this was the Law to before that Statute. And ſo, <hi>Brooke, Tit. Treaſons,</hi> 7. and <hi>Stamford, fo.</hi> 1. <hi>b.</hi> and <hi>Poulton,</hi> and <hi>Dalton</hi> in the places cited, doe report for Law, from the yeere booke 21. <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>fo.</hi> 23.24. That, <hi>If a man accompanied with a convenient number of perſons, doe ride towards the King, to help him in his warrs, and another doth encounter him, and kill him, this is high Treaſon,</hi> alſo it was adjudged <hi>Treaſon</hi> (as they report from the booke of <hi>Aſsiſes,</hi> 22. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Pl.</hi> 49.) before the cited Statute, to <hi>kill the Kings Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, who was ſent to execute his Commandment.</hi> Whereby, we ſee it is <hi>Treaſon,</hi> not only to oppoſe the King, but alſo to oppoſe and kill ſuch, who either take his part, or execute his Commands, in time of warre: And therefore, as every one abominates, the very Name of <hi>Traitor</hi> or <hi>Rebell;</hi> ſo let every one likewiſe be carefull, how he may avoyd thoſe Crimes of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and that he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not with the Authors or Fomenters thereof, in any the kinds before ſpecified. Wherefore conſidering the Premiſſes, If ſo be God ſhould be pleaſed to give us a wicked Prince, and to ſet an evill King over us, (which his Name be ever praiſed for it, as yet we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112910:11"/> have not, and he grant our ſinnes never provoke him to doe it) my advice then grounded upon Scripture, in this caſe, is, That we well pondering that ſaying of King <hi>Salomon, Pro.</hi> 21.1. <hi>The Kings heart is in the hands of the Lord, and he turneth it whitherſoever he will,</hi> (though he never turne them to wickedneſſe) That therefore if he be wickedly bent, we pray unto Almighty God, to diſpoſe and turne his heart right, ſo as it beſt ſeemeth to his godly wiſedome, for our good, over whom he hath ſet him; and then, notwithſtanding our prayers, ſo be he ſtill continueth wicked and evill, Then neither to rebell againſt him, or depoſe him; but only patiently waite the Lords leiſure, till he remove him from us: for, as the Prophets <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Hoſea,</hi> both tell us, <hi>God ſets up Kings, and he taketh away Kings, (therefore we muſt not:) Dan.</hi> 2.21. and <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.11. And true Piety, as it bindes the Subject to deſire a good Sovera gne, ſo likewiſe doth it, to beare with a bad one: which <hi>Tacitus,</hi> (though an Heathen) could tell us, ſaying, Subjects muſt, <hi>Bonos Principes voto expetere, qualeſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tamen tollerare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus briefly, we have ſhewen from the Word of God, That the duty of Subjects to their Lawfull King, is to obey him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as Gods Lieutenant on earth, in all Commands, except directly againſt God, as the Commands of Gods Miniſter; acknowledging him as a Iudge ſet over them by God, and having power to judge them, but to be judged onely by God, to whom alone he muſt give account of his Actions and judgement: and therefore to love him, as their Father; to pray for him, as their protector; for his continuance, if he be good; for his amendment, if he be wicked; following and obeying his Lawfull Commandes; eſchewing and flying his fury, in his unlawfull; without other reſiſtance ſave only <hi>Prayers</hi> &amp; <hi>Teares,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the practiſe &amp; example of the Chriſtians in the Primitive Church, whoſe only Armes and reſiſtance againſt their perſecuting Emperours, were <hi>Preces &amp; Lachrymae:</hi> wherupon ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> excellently, <hi>Coactus repugnare, non novi; Dolere, potero; poteroſlere; potero, gemere: adverſus Arma, Milites; Gothos quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Lachrymae meae A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma ſunt; aliter nec debeo, nec poſſum reſiſtere:</hi> and <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> gives the reaſon, <hi>Quia ſolum hoc contra perſequutorem erat rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dium:</hi> whom the Subjects thought, might ſooner be ſtild and conquered by their Teares and words, then by their Reproofes and Swordes.</p>
            <p>But now perhaps, ſome will object, That this labour might have beene ſpared; foraſmuch (ſay they) as what hath beene here ſpoken,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112910:11"/> concernes private men alone, and not <hi>Magiſtrates:</hi> But to ſuch I anſwer (with him, who is the Glory of this Age, and much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, for his incomparable and exim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous knowledge, both in divine and humane learning, to wit <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi>) That indeed, There have beene found ſome learned men in this Age, as <hi>Peter Maytyr, Pareus</hi> the father, <hi>Iunius Brutus, Daneus,</hi> and ſome others, who have firſt perſwaded themſelves, and then endeavoured to perſwade others, That all which hath beene alleadged, obliges only private Men, but not the Inferiour Magiſtrates; in whom they ſuppoſe to reſide a power, to oppoſe and reſiſt the Injuries of him, who hath the <hi>Supreame power</hi> in a State; yea, and that they offend, if ſo be they doe not; which opinion is not to be admitted or allowed; inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that as it is but meerely an opinion, ſo withall it makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the good, and is deſtructive to the very being of <hi>Peace,</hi> and to the quietneſſe of Government: for if this be admitted, to what a world of miſery ſhould a State continually be ſubjected? For then, any Act of a Kings which the Magiſtrates ſhall pleaſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret, <hi>Injurious to the State,</hi> ſhall immediately become a juſt ground for the people to aſſume armes and rebell; whereby, not onely the publike peace ſhall be unſetled, and the people be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether deprived of its benefits; but alſo a Kings Sacred Perſon, (which ſhould be pretious in his Subjects eyes, as being Gods annointed,) yea, and the whole body of the State, (which would willingly, ever preſerve it ſelfe in ſafety and quiet,) ſhall be both, very often expoſed, not only to diſtraction, but even to deſtruction too; even ſo often as ſeemeth good to the Magiſtrates; many times for ſlight and tollerable matters; yea and it were to be wiſhed, that not ſometimes too for private revenge. And therefore as <hi>Du Bartas,</hi> ſaith very well, <hi>Better it were, to ſuffer ſome diſorder in the Seate, and ſome ſpotts in the Common-wealth, then in pretending to reforme-utterly to overthrow the Republike.</hi> But how ever, though the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may both pretend and intend good, by the taking up armes yet (according to that Divine <hi>Axiom</hi> in Theology) <hi>We muſt not doe evill, that good may enſue.</hi> Wherefore, as the Opinion is nor to be received or allowed of, for the Reaſons premiſed, and ſo) that it is but an opinion, (and mens opinions may be erroneous; ſo alſo is it to be rejected, as being, neither true, nor having any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine example whereon truely to ground it.</p>
            <p>Now, that the Opinion is falſe, and that Magiſtrates have no ſuch
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112910:12"/> power as is pretended, but are alſo bound to obey, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not to reſiſt, as well as the Inferiour ſort of Subjects, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by Reaſon and Scripture: And therefore wee muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and know, That although Magiſtrates; in reſpect of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſort, are publike perſons in a ſtate, yet being oppoſed to the Supreame power, they are but as private men; and in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, the Reaſon of obedience is common both to Magiſtrate and people: For S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.1. when he bids <hi>That every Soule be Subject to the higher powers,</hi> By every Soule, (that is, by Synecdoche, every Man) he doth aſwell meane and include Magiſtrates, as inferiour Subjects: For as Magiſtrates were but private men, till ſuch time Kings conferd that honour and power upon them; ſo that being withdrawne, they are againe rendred but private men in the State.</p>
            <p>Now that Magiſtrates alſo are the Kings Subjects, no man will deny; And that their power is conferd on them, from and by the Supreame, themſelves cannot deny; but, that the Supreame, hath transferred and committed to them, full and lawfull power, to oppoſe and reſiſt him, when, and as often as he doth amiſſe, in their Iudgements, all Men may truly deny; and no man I am ſure can lawfully prove: For all that faculty and power of gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which is placed in the Magiſtrate, is ſo ſubjected to the Supreame power, that whatſoever is done by them, contrary to the will and command of him that rules in cheife, is eſteemed and adjudged, but as the Act of a private man. Celebrions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that ſaying of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and alleadged to this purpoſe by the ſaid <hi>Hugo Grotius. (li.</hi> 1. <hi>de Iure belli &amp; pacis. ca.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.) <hi>Ipſos humanarum rerum gradus adverte; Si aliquidjuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit Curator, faciendum; non tamen, ſi contrà Proconſul jubeat: aut ſi Conſul aliquid Iubeat, &amp; aliud Imperator, non vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contemnis pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem, ſed eligis Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri ſervire: nec hinc debet minor iraſci, ſi major raelatus eſt.</hi> Which alſo is proved by divine authority; for S. <hi>Peter,</hi> when he ſaith; 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.13.14. <hi>Submit your ſelves for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supreams, or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him, &amp;c.</hi> wherein, we ſee he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious both Kings and Magiſtrates, yet would, that we ſhould be Subject and yeeld obedience, (as the words inſinuate,) one way to the King, and another way to the Magiſtrate: to the King, as Supreame in all things, and that without any exception, ſave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112910:12"/> in ſuch things as he Commandes contrary to Gods Will and Word; but to the Magiſtrates, as ſent by him, that is, in reſpect they derive their power, which they have received and poſſeſſe, from the King, and ſo repreſent his Perſon that ſends them: which alſo our Saviour intimates, <hi>Iob</hi> 19.11. Where ſpeaking to <hi>Pilate,</hi> (who was the Magiſtrate, and Deputed to the Government of <hi>Iudea</hi> by <hi>Caeſar,</hi>) he ſaith to him, <hi>Thou couldest have no power at all againſt mee,</hi> (viz. to Iudge mee,) <hi>except it were given thee from above,</hi> that is, as from God, ſo likewiſe from the power above thee, to wit, <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore onely, is it, That by the afore cited Statute of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. <hi>It is declared to be High Treaſon, to kill the Chancellor, Treaſurer, or Juſtice of either Bench, Iuſtice in Eire, or of Aſſiſes,</hi> (who are the grand ſubordinate Magiſtrates of the Realme) <hi>or any other Iuſtices aſſigned to heare and determine, ſitting on the Berch or place of Iudgement, and doing their office:</hi> Becauſe they then repreſent the Kings Perſon. Wherefore, if the King be the Head of the people, according to the Prophet <hi>Samuel;</hi> and the Higher power, according to the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul;</hi> and the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame, according to the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi> then doubtleſſe there is no power equall with his, and much leſſe any power above his, within his Realme and Dominion, and ſo Antiquity confeſſed; for S. <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> tells us, that <hi>Rex non habet parem ſuper terram;</hi> and <hi>Bracton,</hi> that <hi>Rex non habet parem in Regno ſuo,</hi> and he addes the reaſon, <hi>quia ſic amitterat praeceptum, cum par in parem non habet Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium.</hi> Which is alſo graunted and acknowledged by the 37. Article, of the Confeſſion of Faith, made by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>The Kings Majeſty hath the Cheife power in this Realme of England, and other his Dominions, unto whom the Chiefe Government of all Eſtates of this Realme, whether they be Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall or Civill, in all cauſes doth appertaine.</hi> And, the Oracle of the Common Law, Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> doth informe us according to Law, (<hi>li.</hi> 5. <hi>Caudryes caſe fo.</hi> 40. <hi>b.) That it appeareth aſwell by the Ancient Common-lawes of this Realme, by the Reſolutions &amp; Judgements of the Iudges and Sages of the Lawes of England, in all Succeſſion of Ages; as by authority of many acts of Parliament, Ancient, and of latter times, That the Kingdome of England is an abſolute Monarchy, and that the King is the only Supreame Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, aſwell over Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112910:13"/> as Temporall, within this Realme.</hi> And truely the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, (which ordained by Act of Parliament, And which by force of the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz. ca.</hi> 1. Every Magiſtrate, within this Realme of <hi>England</hi> is to take,) makes it alſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, for hee that takes it doth declare in his Conſcience, <hi>That the Kings Highneſſe, is the onely Supreame Governour of this Realme, and of all other his Highneſſe Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as well in all Spirituall and Eccleſiaſticall things or cauſes, as Temporall.</hi> And therefore ſurely, if Magiſtrates acknowledge a power above themſelves, (as they who have tooke that Oath, cannot deny but they have) then doubtleſſe, They are not to Governe him, but rather to Governe for him, according to that power he hath committed to them, and then conſequently, be both bound to obey, and forbid to reſiſt that Supreame and Higher power, aſwell as other private Subjects be; wherefore whatever hath beene ſaid, in reſpect of their duty, doth aſwell concerne Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>And further, as there is no cleare Text, that declares it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to reſiſt the Higher power, in any caſe; ſo neither is there any Divine and appoſite example in Scripture, that I could ever meete with yet (no, not alleadged by the adverſe partie in maintanance of their opinion,) whereon truely to ground ſuch an opinion, and proove ſuch a Lawfull power, to oppoſe the Supreame, and to reſide in the Inferiour Magiſtracy, or Optima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a Realme: but on the Contrary, much may be ſaid and deduced from thence, to diſproove, and evince that poſition: In contradiction whereof, S. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> hath afoorded us a good obſervation, <hi>(Homil.</hi> 2. <hi>in Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Timoth.) Inſurrexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt adverſus Aaron poſt vituli formatam effigiem, Core, Dathan &amp; Abiron; quid ergo? nonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> illi periere? &amp;c.</hi> Saith hee; It was after That <hi>Aaron</hi> had ſinned fooliſhly and hainouſly, in making the Calfe, that <hi>Core, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiron</hi> rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; but what then? did they not periſh? Yes, they did; and that was to ſhew, that although the Governour might be wicked, yet it was not for them who were under him, to take upon them, to correct him, or rebell againſt him; no, though they were the Optimates and Peeres of a Realme; for wee know the Two hundred and fifty Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that joyned in the Conſpiracy and Rebellion againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112910:13"/> 
               <hi>Aaron,</hi> periſhed aſwell, yea and as ſtrangely too, as <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company. And beſides, among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> where, though there were ſo many Kings, who were no leſſe contemners of the Divine, then of humane Lawes, doe wee read, that ever the Inferiour Magiſtrates (amongſt whom, there were no doubt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> many godly and valiant men,) did at any time aſſume power to oppoſe their Kings, but only when they received a ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God, who alone hath power above Kings, and to correct them: Nor ever read wee, that the Statues and Idolls of the falſe Gods, which were publikely ſet up by the Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were dejected or demoliſhed, but by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the good Kings which God gave them, when they came to rule over the people. And ſo wee ſee, That Idolatry continued in the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and no reformation, from the time of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Nebat,</hi> and firſt King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne, and ſet up the two <hi>Golden Calves and the Altar at Bethel,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.28.33. untill the time of good <hi>Ioſiah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> who demoliſhed them, as we read, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 23.15. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.7. according to the Word of the Lord, ſpoken by the man of God, which Propheſied againſt the <hi>Altar at Bethel,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 13.2. after they had continued above the ſpace of 300. yeares: during which time, doubtleſſe, there were many Religious men and Magiſtrates in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and yet notwithſtanding, we read not of any that oppoſed the King, though an Idolater, nor yet that tooke upon them to remove the Idolls from amongſt them, till ſuch time it pleaſed God, to ſend King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> to doe it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as he had foretold by the Prophet: but it is to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that during that ſpace, every good man, only looked to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he polluted not his own ſoule by ſuch ſpirituall whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and withall reſolved and endeavoured with <hi>Joſua, (Ioſua</hi> 24.15.) <hi>That He and his houſhould, might ſerve the Lord,</hi> If then Idolatry, and defection from God, tyranny over the people, and perſecution of the Saints for their profeſſion, hindred not the Spirit of God, to Command the people to yeild due and hearty obedience to their cruell Kings, as we have ſhewen, before from <hi>Ieremiah</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> towards <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> and <hi>Nero;</hi> what ſhameleſſe preſumption then is it, to any Chriſtian people, now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, to claime ſuch an unlawfull liberty and power, to reſiſt, oppoſe or depoſe their lawfull Kings, which God refuſed to grant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112910:14"/> to his own peculiar and choſen people the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For in the firſt Booke of <hi>Samuel,</hi> in the 8. Chapter, where <hi>Samuel</hi> makes the diſcription of a King, and ſhewes the people the manner of their King that ſhould Raigne over them (not that all things there mentioned by <hi>Samuel</hi> from the Lord, were by him granted as lawful for a King to do, but <hi>Samuel</hi> relates the maner) therby to prepare their hearts before hand, to the due obedience of that King, which God was to give unto them, &amp; ſo he there openeth to them, what might be the intollerable quallities, that might happen either in him, or ſome other of their Kings, through their inordinate appetites,) thereby preparing them to patience, and not to reſiſt <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> if ſo be the licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of their Kings will, ſhould extend ſo far as to do ſuch things as hee there mentioneth; as if he would have ſaid; Since God hath granted your importunate ſuite in giving you a King; as yee have formerly committed an error, in ſhaking of Gods yoke and over-haſty ſeeking of a King: ſo now beware, yee fall not into the next alſo, in caſting off raſhly, that yoke, which God at your earneſt ſuite hath layd upon you, how hard ſo ever it ſeemes to be: for as you could not have obtained a King, without the permiſſion and ordinance of God; ſo in no wiſe, can yee ſhake him off without the ſame warrant: ſince hee, that hath the only power to make him, hath alſo, alone the power to unmake him; and therefore bee yee obedient, and patiently beare with thoſe ſtraights that I ſhall fore-ſhew you, as with the finger and hand of God, which lyeth not in your power to take off: For ſaith he, <hi>verſe.</hi> 11. <hi>This will be the manner of your King, that ſhall raigne over you; Hee will take your ſonnes, &amp; appoint them for himſelfe, for his Charriots, and to be his horſemen, and ſome ſhall runne before his Charriots, &amp;c.</hi> That is briefly, Hee will exerciſe very much cruelty, oppreſſion and Tyranny over you, almoſt beyond hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane patience to endure; But yet for all this, although hee ſhould doo ſo, Yet wee doe not at all read there, That the People ſhould then diſobey him; neither of any liberty granted to them, or power granted to the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> to oppoſe him for ſo doing, or to reſtraine his power, or to redreſſe thoſe evills themſelves, but being deſtitute of all humane Remedies, they were onely, to <hi>cry unto the Lord,</hi> to remedy them; as wee reade at <hi>verſe</hi> the 18. For indeed there is no Lawfull way of redreſſe, but by our addreſſes to God by prayer, to turne his heart; and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112910:14"/> to the King by petition, to reforme his actions? and ſo our owne old Law teacheth us, for <hi>Bracton, li</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the King, ſaith thus, <hi>Si ab eo petatur, locus erit Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicationi, quod factum ſuum corrigat &amp; emendet, quod quidem ſi non fecerit, ſatis ſufficit ei ad poenam, quod Dominum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectet ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orem: Nemo quidem de factis ſuis praeſumat diſputare, multo fortius contra factum ſuum ire.</hi> And therefore it is very remarkeable, that amongſt the many Prophets, that God ſent to reprehend the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> for their Idolatry, Cruelty, and Oppreſſion, how wicked ſoever the Kings were; yet never any of them called upon the people, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Elders of the people, to reſiſt, or oppoſe them: but whereas it ſeemed good to God, to puniſh the wicked Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> for their great ſinnes, (whereof ſome were, oppreſſion of their ſubjects) wee read that hee did it by the <hi>Aſſirians,</hi> by the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> by the <hi>Babylonians</hi> and not by the Iewes their Subjects; to teach us, That hee teacheth us not Rebellion and diſobedience, nor is the author thereof; and withall. That wee ſhould not take upon us to remedy ſuch things, but to leave that to him, to whom Vengeance belongeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.1. <hi>For Vengeance is mine, and I will repay ſaith the Lord, Deut.</hi> 32.35. and againe, by S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 12.19. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.30. And if at any time, Acts of violence were committed upon the Perſons of wicked Kings, ſo that they were killed, yet we doe not ever read, That God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of the murder, but Contrariwiſe, that hee puniſhed the doers thereof: nor are ſuch paſſages recorded in Sacred ſtory, in approbation of the fact, but onely as a Teſtimony of Divine providence, ſometimes permitting it: and ſo wee read, that the ſervants of King <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.25. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt him, and ſlew him on his bed. But ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, onely ſhew us what was done by others, not what ought to be done by us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but on the contrary, the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> by his owne example, ſhewes what the duty of <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> is towards their King, though a wicked Man; even to honour him before the people: when as, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.30. The Elders and the people looking on him, hee yet yeelds his wonted reverence toward King <hi>Saul,</hi> though a wicked perſon, and having alſo, but newly tranſgreſſed Gods holy Commandes.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:112910:15"/>
            <p>Remarkeable alſo, is that paſſage recorded by all the Evangeliſts, and which we read of, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.50 51. <hi>Marc.</hi> 14.47. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.50.51 and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.10.11. where, when as <hi>Simon Peter drew forth his ſword and cut of Malcus his eare, who was the Servant of the high Prieſt,</hi> our Lord and Maſter, immediatly <hi>touched his eare, and healed him againe,</hi> and withall rebuked <hi>Peter, bidding him put up his ſword:</hi> Now in that he healed the High Prieſt ſervants Eare againe; it was to ſhew us, as the Power of his Divinity by the Cure, ſo alſo, that <hi>Peter</hi> had offended by cutting it off: But in that he bidds <hi>Peter</hi> to put up his ſword againe; it was to teach us, That if ſuch who have the Supreame Power and Authority, doe unjuſtly injure us, wee ſhould rather beare it with patience, then reſiſt them by violence. For as Chriſt there ſaith to <hi>Peter, They which take the ſword</hi> (viz. to reſiſt authority, as <hi>Peter</hi> did, though in a good cauſe to defend our moſt innocent Saviour) <hi>ſhall periſh with the Sword;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>They that reſiſt the powers, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, weighing the premiſes, and that even <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are but as private Men, in reſpect of the King, and ſo aſwell bound to obey him, as his Inferiour Subjects; Therefore to conclude, let every Subject, whether, <hi>Magiſtrate, Optimate,</hi> or <hi>Infimate,</hi> conceive &amp; apprehend himſelfe in the Condition of a private Man, (as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he is, when oppoſed to the Supreame,) and then, if he would faine preſerve himſelfe ſafe, from offending either God, his owne Conſcience, or the King, and ſo perſerve himſelfe from error, then I am ſure, he cannot have a more ſafe, or better example to follow, then that which <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> our moſt bleſſed Lord &amp; Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath ſhewen us, whom we all doe ſtedfaſtly beleeve, to have been, moſt holy, juſt, innocent and inoffenſive; and yet, though hee was not only, ever falſly accuſed, &amp; being once ſaid to have a Divell, &amp; ſhameleſſely abuſed, as being mocked, ſcoffed at, blinded, and then ſpit on; but alſo undeſervedly puniſhed, as being buffeted, ſcourged, &amp; crowned with thornes, yet did endure all thoſe opprobries, injuries, &amp; puniſhments, with ſo great patience; as that, though we read. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.53. <hi>He could have had more then twelve Legions of Angels,</hi> to have defended him, but for praying for; yet we never read, That he did reſiſt, and but ſeldome, that he ſo much as anſwered againe: And S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.21. tells us, <hi>That Chriſt hath ſuffered for us, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps;</hi> which if we doe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112910:15"/> Then the Comfort and Reſult will be, <hi>That if wee Suffer with him,</hi> or for him, or for his ſake, <hi>We ſbaell alſo raigne with him,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, 2 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <q>Berchetus in explicat. controver. Gallicanae cap. <hi>7.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe teſtimonies are cleere enough, and yet to all theſe I will adde this one memorable example, which you may read in <hi>Berche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and <hi>Ioh. Servivus,</hi> which tells us, that in <hi>France,</hi> after the great <hi>Maſſacre</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> when the reformed Religion did ſeeme as it were forſaken, and almoſt exſtinguiſhed, a cerraine King powerfull in ſtrength, rich in wealth, and terrible for his Ships, and navall force, which was at enmitie and hatred with the King of <hi>France,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched a ſolemne Embaſſie and meſſage unto <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre,</hi> &amp; other Proteſtant Lords, and commanded his Embaſſadours to do their beſt to ſet the Proteſtants againſt the Paſtiſts, and to arme <hi>Henry</hi> the Prince of <hi>Navarre,</hi> which then lived at <hi>Bearne,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Dominion of the moſt Chriſtian King, againſt his Soveraigne, the <hi>French King,</hi> which thing the Embaſſadours indeavoured to doe, withall there art and skill, but all in vaine; for <hi>Henry</hi> being a good Subject, as it were another <hi>David,</hi> to become a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent King, would not prevent the day of his Lord; yet the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors offered him many ample, faire, and magnificent conditions; among the reſt, abundance of Money, the ſuume of three hundred thouſand, <hi>anreorum ſcutatorum, French</hi> crownes, which were ready to be told for the preparation of the warre; and for the continuation of the ſame, there ſhould be payd every Moneth ſo much as was neceſſary; but <hi>Henry</hi> being a faithfull Chriſtian, a good Prince, a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dower, and though he was diſplaced, from the publike government of the common-wealth; and for his ſake, for the diſlike the King bare towards him, the King had baniſhed many Proteſtants from his Country, and had killed many faithfull Paſtors; yet would not he for all this lift up his hand againſt the Lords annointed; but refuſed their Gold, rejected their conditions, and diſmiſſed their Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, as witneſſes of his faith to God, his fedility and allegiance to his King, and peaceable mind towards his Country,</p>
            <p>The ſumme then of all, which hath beene ſaid, is this; That ſo be, the licentious will of a King, be not terminated by Gods Law, and the Law of that Republike over which God hath ſet him, but that he will needs ſwerue from both rules: that then his Subjects pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not to oppoſe his unjuſt commands, by an unlawfull Sedition
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112910:16"/> or Rebellion, which is moſt odious in the ſight of God and Men; but rather by ſlight, or paſſive obedience; according to Gods Word, and his peoples example; by both which, we ſuppoſe the point hath beene clearely proved: which if we do, then may we ſtand up with cleane hands and unſpotted conſciences, having proved our ſelves in all our actions, true Chriſtians towardes God, and dutifull Subjects towards our King, having remitted the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and puniſhment of all his wrongs to us, unto him to whom onely of right it appertaineth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Almighty and Everlaſting God, who haſt taught us by thy Word, that the hearts of Kings are in thy rule and governance, and that thou doſt diſpoſe and turne them, as it ſeemeth beſt to thy godly wiſedome: therefore wee humbly beſeech thee ſo to diſpoſe and governe the heart of <hi>CHARLES,</hi> thy Servant, our King and Governour, that he knowing whoſe Miniſter he is, may in all his thoughts, words and workes, ever ſeeke thy honour and glory, and ſtudy to preſerve thy people committed to his charge, in wealth peace, and godlines; and grant that wee his Subjects, duely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering whoſe Authority he hath, may faithfully ſerve, honour, and humbly obey him, in thee, and for thee, aceording to thy bleſſed Word and Ordinance, through <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112910:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
